<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Byzantique</title><link>https://byzantique.com/</link><description>Recent content on Byzantique</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 18:51:08 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://byzantique.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Toledot Formula</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/themes/toledot/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 08:47:10 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/themes/toledot/</guid><description>The Toledot formula refers to the Hebrew word תּוֹלֵדוֹת (toledot), which means &amp;ldquo;descendants,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;histories,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;generations&amp;rdquo; (in reference to successors, usually introducing a geneaological list and related narratives) and various occurrences of it are thought to divide Genesis into 10–12 sections.
The occurrences in Genesis occur at:
2:4 (heavens and the earth); some don&amp;rsquo;t consider this instance to be a section marker 5:1 (Adam) 6:9 (Noah) 10:1 (Noah&amp;rsquo;s sons: Shem, Ham, Japheth); it also occurs at 10:32 but this is thought to be part of this &amp;ldquo;section&amp;rdquo; 11:10 (Shem) 11:27 (Terah, father of Abraham) 25:12–13 (Abraham&amp;rsquo;s son: Ishmael) 25:19 (Abraham&amp;rsquo;s son: Isaac, father of Jacob); some don&amp;rsquo;t consider this instance to be a section marker 36:1 (Isaac&amp;rsquo;s son: Esau); it also occurs at 36:9 and specifically emphasizes Esau as the father of the Edomites, but some consider this to be part of this same section 37:2 (Isaac&amp;rsquo;s son: Jacob, father of Joseph); some don&amp;rsquo;t consider this instance to be a section marker Learn more Peter Leithart, &amp;ldquo;Toledoth and the Structure of Genesis.</description></item><item><title>The First Murder, Cain's Lineage, and Birth of Seth (Genesis 4:8–26)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/4/8/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 19:31:21 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/4/8/</guid><description>The First Murder (4:8–15) Translation Notes Cain&amp;rsquo;s Lineage and Birth of Seth (4:16–26) Translation Notes The First Murder (4:8–15) Lectionary 2nd Tuesday of Great Lent Translation Genesis 4:8–15 (ENGLXXUP), altered 8 And Cain said to Abel his brother, Let us go out into the plain; and it came to pass that when they were in the plain Cain rose up against Abel his brother, and [killeda] him. 9 And the Lord God said to Cain, Where is Abel thy brother?</description></item><item><title>Exiled from Paradise and First Children (Genesis 3:21–4:7)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/3/21/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 09:40:30 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/3/21/</guid><description>Exiled from Paradise (3:21–3:24) Translation Notes God clothed Adam and Eve Expulsion from the Garden The First Children (4:1–7) Translation Notes Lectionary 2nd Monday of Great Lent This entire pericope (3:21–4:7) is read during Vespers on the second Monday of Great Lent, but it has been subdivided on this page for the purpose of providing more organized commentary.
Exiled from Paradise (3:21–3:24) Translation Genesis 3:21–24 (ENGLXXUP), altered 21 And the Lord God made for Adam and his wife garments of skin, and clothed them.</description></item><item><title>Creation of Eve &amp; The Fall (Genesis 2:20–3:20)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/2/20/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 03:12:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/2/20/</guid><description>Creation of Eve (Zoe / Life) (2:20–24) Translation Notes The serpent and the Fall of humanity (3:1–20) Translation Notes Lectionary 1st Friday of Great Lent This entire pericope (2:20–3:20) is read during Vespers on the first Friday of Great Lent, but it has been subdivided on this page for the purpose of providing more organized commentary.
Creation of Eve (Zoe / Life) (2:20–24) Translation Genesis 2:20–25 (ENGLXXUP), altered 20 And Adam gave names to all the cattle and to all the birds of the sky, and to all the wild beasts of the field, but for Adam there was not found a help like to himself.</description></item><item><title>Creation (Genesis 1:1–2:19)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/1/1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 16:37:05 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/1/1/</guid><description>Days 1–3 (1:1–13) Translation Notes Symmetry Functional vs. materialist ontology Leitwort Days 4–5 (1:14–23) Translation Notes Days 6–7 (1:24–2:3) Translation Notes God&amp;rsquo;s image and likeness Sabbath Creation of Adam (2:4–19) Translation Notes Days 1–3 (1:1–13) Lectionary 1st Monday of Great Lent (i.e., Clean Monday, Beginning of the Great Fast) Translation Genesis 1:1–13 (ENGLXXUP), altered 1 In the beginning God made the heaven and the earth. 2 But the earth was [unseena] and unfurnished, and darkness was over the deep, and the Spirit of God moved over the water.</description></item><item><title>Common Abbreviations</title><link>https://byzantique.com/abbrev/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 02:15:36 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/abbrev/</guid><description>Abbreviation Citation Alter Robert Alter, ed., The Hebrew Bible: A Translation with Commentary, 3 volumes (New York; London: W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company, 2019). ANE Ancient Near East(ern) ANT See &amp;ldquo;PATr&amp;rdquo; B4E N.T. Wright. The Bible for Everyone: A New Translation. London: SPCK, 2018. BDAG Arndt, William, Frederick W. Danker, Walter Bauer, and F. Wilbur Gingrich. A Greek-English Lexicon of the New Testament and Other Early Christian Literature. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2000.</description></item><item><title>Luke 8:22–56</title><link>https://byzantique.com/nt/gospels/luke/8/22/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 00:07:18 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/nt/gospels/luke/8/22/</guid><description>Master over storms (8:22–25) Translation Notes Encounter with the Gadarenes demoniac (8:26–39) Translation Notes Jairus&amp;rsquo; daughter raised from the dead and woman with bleeding issue healed (8:40–56) Translation Notes This pericope begins a section of multiple accounts demonstrating Jesus&amp;rsquo; power over nature / primordial chaos (wind and waves; vv. 22–25), unclean spirits (vv. 26–39), disease, and death (vv. 40–56).
Master over storms (8:22–25) Lectionary 21st Wednesday after Pentecost Translation Luke 8:22–25 (TCENT) 22 One day Jesus got into a boat with his disciples and said to them, &amp;ldquo;Let us cross over to the other side of the lake.</description></item><item><title>Privacy Policy</title><link>https://byzantique.com/privacy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 17:00:25 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/privacy/</guid><description>Last updated: March 29, 2023
This website, its hosting provider(s), and/or related sites (e.g., sites hosting resources used on this site; collectively &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo;) may collect certain Usage Data that could potentially be used to contact or identify you. Usage Data are automatically collected when using this website.
When you visit this website, it is also visiting you. Because I don&amp;rsquo;t maintain my own server, develop my own website framework, etc., I rely on third-party hosting and other service providers.</description></item><item><title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/faqs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 16:41:57 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/faqs/</guid><description>What does the site name mean? Is this site affiliated with or endorsed by any specific church, religion, movement, organization, political party, color, musical genre, etc.? Who are you? How do I contact you? What inspired you to make this website? Why do you use archaic language in the Old Testament? What does this abbreviation mean? Why is there a weird letter &amp;lsquo;u&amp;rsquo; in quotes from the Bible? Where can I learn more about Eastern Orthodox Christianity?</description></item><item><title>Contact</title><link>https://byzantique.com/contact/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 18:50:32 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/contact/</guid><description>Why would you want to? 😛 Just kidding: feel free to reach out—unless you&amp;rsquo;re a jerk.
Email me Tweet @ me Alternative email address My email address is qohelet_dot_dan_at_pm_dot_me. There’s no underscores in my actual email address.
Why did you write your email address like that? Because jerks write spam bots that troll the Internet looking for email addresses to send junk mail to. It also thwarts people who can’t figure out how to swap out ‘at’ with ‘@’ and ‘dot’ with a period, but I’m not so sure that’s a bad thing.</description></item><item><title>Perspective</title><link>https://byzantique.com/welcome/perspective/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 18:50:25 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/welcome/perspective/</guid><description>Approach What do you believe? What is the nous (νοῦς)? Affiliation John 5:39–40 (BTV) [Jesus said,] &amp;ldquo;You search the Scriptures because you think that in them you have eternal life, and it is these that testify about me, yet you are not willing to come to me so that you may have life.&amp;rdquo; Approach I am an Eastern Orthodox Christian and so approach Scripture from a Byzantine Christian perspective.</description></item><item><title>Texts and Translations</title><link>https://byzantique.com/welcome/texts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 18:50:13 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/welcome/texts/</guid><description>This page does not contain an exhaustive list, but I primarily consult and comment upon these specific texts and translations.
While these are not the only texts consulted, these are the ones I primarily read. I predominantly quote the Scriptures from public domain texts or from works licensed in ways that don&amp;rsquo;t heavily restrict my ability to cite them (e.g., Creative Commons licenses, copyright licenses explicitly allowing usage by Orthodox Christians for nonprofit purposes, etc.</description></item></channel></rss>