<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Genesis on Byzantique</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/</link><description>Recent content in Genesis on Byzantique</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2023 08:55:36 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Toledot Formula</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/themes/toledot/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 08:47:10 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/themes/toledot/</guid><description>The Toledot formula refers to the Hebrew word תּוֹלֵדוֹת (toledot), which means &amp;ldquo;descendants,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;histories,&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;generations&amp;rdquo; (in reference to successors, usually introducing a geneaological list and related narratives) and various occurrences of it are thought to divide Genesis into 10–12 sections.
The occurrences in Genesis occur at:
2:4 (heavens and the earth); some don&amp;rsquo;t consider this instance to be a section marker 5:1 (Adam) 6:9 (Noah) 10:1 (Noah&amp;rsquo;s sons: Shem, Ham, Japheth); it also occurs at 10:32 but this is thought to be part of this &amp;ldquo;section&amp;rdquo; 11:10 (Shem) 11:27 (Terah, father of Abraham) 25:12–13 (Abraham&amp;rsquo;s son: Ishmael) 25:19 (Abraham&amp;rsquo;s son: Isaac, father of Jacob); some don&amp;rsquo;t consider this instance to be a section marker 36:1 (Isaac&amp;rsquo;s son: Esau); it also occurs at 36:9 and specifically emphasizes Esau as the father of the Edomites, but some consider this to be part of this same section 37:2 (Isaac&amp;rsquo;s son: Jacob, father of Joseph); some don&amp;rsquo;t consider this instance to be a section marker Learn more Peter Leithart, &amp;ldquo;Toledoth and the Structure of Genesis.</description></item><item><title>The First Murder, Cain's Lineage, and Birth of Seth (Genesis 4:8–26)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/4/8/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2023 19:31:21 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/4/8/</guid><description>The First Murder (4:8–15) Translation Notes Cain&amp;rsquo;s Lineage and Birth of Seth (4:16–26) Translation Notes The First Murder (4:8–15) Lectionary 2nd Tuesday of Great Lent Translation Genesis 4:8–15 (ENGLXXUP), altered 8 And Cain said to Abel his brother, Let us go out into the plain; and it came to pass that when they were in the plain Cain rose up against Abel his brother, and [killeda] him. 9 And the Lord God said to Cain, Where is Abel thy brother?</description></item><item><title>Exiled from Paradise and First Children (Genesis 3:21–4:7)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/3/21/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 09:40:30 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/3/21/</guid><description>Exiled from Paradise (3:21–3:24) Translation Notes God clothed Adam and Eve Expulsion from the Garden The First Children (4:1–7) Translation Notes Lectionary 2nd Monday of Great Lent This entire pericope (3:21–4:7) is read during Vespers on the second Monday of Great Lent, but it has been subdivided on this page for the purpose of providing more organized commentary.
Exiled from Paradise (3:21–3:24) Translation Genesis 3:21–24 (ENGLXXUP), altered 21 And the Lord God made for Adam and his wife garments of skin, and clothed them.</description></item><item><title>Creation of Eve &amp; The Fall (Genesis 2:20–3:20)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/2/20/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 03:12:02 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/2/20/</guid><description>Creation of Eve (Zoe / Life) (2:20–24) Translation Notes The serpent and the Fall of humanity (3:1–20) Translation Notes Lectionary 1st Friday of Great Lent This entire pericope (2:20–3:20) is read during Vespers on the first Friday of Great Lent, but it has been subdivided on this page for the purpose of providing more organized commentary.
Creation of Eve (Zoe / Life) (2:20–24) Translation Genesis 2:20–25 (ENGLXXUP), altered 20 And Adam gave names to all the cattle and to all the birds of the sky, and to all the wild beasts of the field, but for Adam there was not found a help like to himself.</description></item><item><title>Creation (Genesis 1:1–2:19)</title><link>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/1/1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 16:37:05 -0500</pubDate><guid>https://byzantique.com/ot/pentateuch/genesis/1/1/</guid><description>Days 1–3 (1:1–13) Translation Notes Symmetry Functional vs. materialist ontology Leitwort Days 4–5 (1:14–23) Translation Notes Days 6–7 (1:24–2:3) Translation Notes God&amp;rsquo;s image and likeness Sabbath Creation of Adam (2:4–19) Translation Notes Days 1–3 (1:1–13) Lectionary 1st Monday of Great Lent (i.e., Clean Monday, Beginning of the Great Fast) Translation Genesis 1:1–13 (ENGLXXUP), altered 1 In the beginning God made the heaven and the earth. 2 But the earth was [unseena] and unfurnished, and darkness was over the deep, and the Spirit of God moved over the water.</description></item></channel></rss>